<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="44"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





               PRINCIPAL'S MESSAGE

               Dear Students,

               Education shapes us into evolved individuals and promising citizens. It expands our mental
               horizons,  enhances  sensitivity  towards  our  fellow  beings  and  enables  us  to  effectively
               contribute  to  the  world we  all are a  part of.  It  is  not  merely an intellectual  pursuit, but
               involves shaping of values, character, skills and perspective. At Maitreyi College, learning is
               defined by, but not limited to the degree and other courses offered by us in the disciplines of
               Science, Commerce and Humanities. Education here is an experience that prepares young
               women to venture into the world on the strength of their knowledge, character and vision.

               At Maitreyi, we are a family, a ‘kutumb’, where everyone is committed to the cause of growth
               and learning. As you join this institution, you will find yourself surrounded with a wide range
               of opportunities. What stands out is the training in research that has been a significant recent
               step. With a dedicated research cell and a research journal of our own, we believe in training
               academics young. Your journey in this institution, at all times, will be supplemented with the
               necessary  support  and  guidance  from  the  members  of  our  staff.  Teachers  work  with
               dedication and commitment, helping you master not just your subject, but also acquire the
               ability to think for yourselves and evolve your own unique point of view. With a robust
               background in research and pedagogy, teachers at Maitreyi are academic experts, who have
               made a mark in both national and international scholarship. The administrative staff works
               tirelessly,  facilitating  your  smooth  transition  from  school  to  college.  Also,  the  lush  and
               vibrant environs of our college are merely a visual delight. They symbolize the central role
               of nature in human life, a fact we all must respect and adequately acknowledge.

               Our College has seen tremendous growth in recent years. Four of our Science departments
               have been awarded STAR status by the Department of Biotechnology, Govt. of India. Maitreyi
               College has also been accredited with 'A' grade by the National Assessment and Accreditation
               Council. The College was graded after a close scrutiny of teaching methods, research skills of
               the faculty and students, student progression and infrastructural development. This grade is
               a testimony to the perseverance, devotion and commitment to the cause of education.

               At Maitreyi, we believe in being early adaptors, updating pedagogical strategies to suit the
               evolving  trends  and  needs.  Theory  must  meet  application,  in  order  to  make  learning
               experience a comprehensive one. And with the right approach, dear students, you have the
               opportunity of re/discovering your potential and sharpening your acumen in both curricular
               and extra-curricular aspects. You will find a host of platforms offered to you by the college,
               at  both  inter  and  intra-college  levels.  Addressing  the  increasing  relevance  of
               interdisciplinarity,  the  College  has  also  recently  conceptualized  a  one  of  its  kind
               interdisciplinary  academic  fest  'Avgaahan'.  As  a  student  of  Maitreyi  College,  you  must
               familiarize yourself with these diverse opportunities made available to you and make the
               most of them.




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 1]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               With the University continuing in the online mode, as per guidelines, we have been following
               the online model for both, the admissions and teaching. Mindful of diverse students joining
               our  College,  we  have  a  well-structured  mechanism  for  a  smooth  execution  of  online
               processes, along with the requisite support resources.

               On behalf of the Maitreyi kutumb, I welcome you to the institution! With zeal in your heart
               and commitment in thought, I hope you shall make the most of your education at Maitreyi
               College. You come to us as  fledglings, undergo training, you grow and finally emerge  as
               beautiful birds ready to soar high and scale new heights. I am confident that each of you will
               make an indelible mark, in your own unique way, making your parents, institution and your
               country proud!

                                                                                                Best Wishes
                                                                                       Dr. Haritma Chopra






               VIDUSHI MAITREYI

               Maitreyi College, a constituent College of the University of Delhi, was founded in 1967 by the
               Delhi administration. The College community is proud to bear the name of Maitreyi, who was
               an eminent scholar of the Vedic period and the wife of sage Yajnavalakya. She had keen
               interest in philosophical knowledge and cultivated a thirst for theological truths since early
               age. She was interested in gaining knowledge of the Vedas, Upanishads and Sastras. Maitreyi
               chose knowledge over worldly possessions, when asked by her husband to make a choice
               between the two.

               The great Maitreyi Upanishad is a contribution to the world of theology which explains with
               many  analogies  and  metaphors  the  concept  of  self,  atman,  as  the  ultimate  reality,
               emphasizing the value of renunciation. The dialogue between Maitreyi and Yajnavalakya in
               Brihadaranyaka Upanishad shows her as an empowered woman, determined to attain self-
               realization  through knowledge. It  has been  our objective to  weave these values  into the
               fabric of our education system, which is a blend of the best of tradition and modernity.











                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 2]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                CONTENTS


                S. NO.  TOPICS                                                                  PAGE NO.

                     1  About the College                                                        4
                     2  Courses Offered                                                          5

                     3  Admission Criteria                                                       6

                     4  Admission Procedure                                                      7
                     5  Fees and Other Charges                                                   18

                     6  Terms of Payment                                                         20

                     7  Rules of Discipline and Attendance                                       21

                     8  Examination and Promotion                                                22
                     9  Scholarships and Prizes                                                  22

                    10  Academic Activities                                                      24

                    11  Extra-curricular Activities                                              26

                    12  Facilities                                                               29
                    13  Departments and Faculty                                                  34

                    14  Optional Subjects/ Papers                                                37









                        Ragging is strictly prohibited and will invite suspension from College.

                Any ragging incident may immediately be reported to Students' Union office bearers,
                                    Grievance Committee members or the Principal.

                                              Nodal Officer Dr. Versha Goel
                                         vgoel@maitreyi.du.ac.in;  9818266521





                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 3]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                ABOUT THE COLLEGE

               The College made a modest beginning at Netaji Nagar with a staff of seventeen teachers
               offering only B.A. (Pass) and B.Sc. (General) courses. It has since made rapid progress both
               in size and stature. Presently the College campus in Chanakyapuri is spread over ten acres of
               land in lush green surroundings with extensive playgrounds and open spaces. We have a
               distinguished faculty and an efficient and supportive non-teaching staff.
               The College offers Honours in Science, Commerce and Humanities at the undergraduate level
               and also postgraduate courses in Mathematics and Political Science. Certificate and diploma
               courses in Journalism, French, Spanish and Web-designing are offered as non-credit add-on
               courses. There is provision for remedial coaching classes for benefit of students as and when
               they  require  it.  For  an  all-round  development  of  our  students,  several  programmes  are
               initiated  to  increase  awareness  about  health  and  fitness,  legal  aid  services,  disaster
               management and self-defense.
               The College has many 'firsts' to its credit- it is the first College in the University of Delhi to
               offer PG Diploma in Nanotechnology and the first to adopt e-learning methodology to create
               teaching material and evaluation quizzes for which an e-lab has also been set up. Our College
               also initiated an endeavour to bridge the gap between disciplines through 'Avgaahan', a first
               of its kind interdisciplinary academic fest. With an aim to inculcate research and analytical
               skills of students, College instituted its 'Research and Incubation Centre' in 2018. The College
               has also organised the first ever Tedx event with the theme "A Proposal Towards Humanity".
               Through  various  training  programs  and  activities,  the  college  bridges  the  gap  between
               industry  and  academics  by  contributing  to  the  growth  and  personality  development  of
               students through departmental magazines, summer research projects and various start-up
               initiatives by the Entrepreneurship Cell.
               Apart  from  our  excellence  in academics,  we  have  an  established  tradition  of  continuous
               achievements  in  the  fields  of  sports,  NCC,  NSS  and  cultural  activities.  The  College  has
               established  sports  centre  and  facility  dedicated  to  promote  ‘netball’  among  young  and
               enthusiastic girls of our country. This facility has been named ‘Pragati’, and aims to impart
               physical ability as well as techniques and training for playing netball in India. Country's first
               ‘Sashakt’  Nodal  Sports  Centre  for  PwD  has  been  running  at  Maitreyi  College,  in  which
               national and international level paralympic & basketball players practice. We look forward
               to the whole-hearted participation and involvement of our students in the academic and
               cultural life of the College.
               As a part of outreach activity, Maitreyi College has collaborated with Sanskriti School with
               an  objective  of  providing  life  skill  training  and  hands  on  learning  opportunities  to  the
               children with special needs of Sanskriti School wherein they put up a food stall in our College
               once a month.
               The new four-storey science block is set to be operational soon, which comprises of fully
               equipped laboratories, lecture theatres, class rooms and faculty rooms. Professor Yogesh
               Tyagi, Vice Chancellor, University of Delhi laid the foundation stone of hostel recently. The
               four  storey  residential  facility  would  house  94  students.  It  will  have  reading  room,
               gymnasium,  a  common  room  for  recreation,  an  activity  room,  dining  hall,  kitchen  and
               warden's  residence.  The  hostel  would  accommodate  both  National  and  International
               students and rooms would be allocated on the basis of merit and distance from the College.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 4]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                COURSES OFFERED


                 S. No.  Course Name                                   Number of Seats
                                                   UR     SC  ST      OBC  EWS  PwD*         Sports*    ECA*
                 1       B.A. (Programme)          93     34  17      62     25     11       8          3
                 2       B.A. (H) Economics        23     9     4     15     6      3        2          1

                 3       B.A. (H) English          23     9     4     15     6      3        2          1
                 4       B.A. (H) Hindi            23     9     4     15     6      3        2          1
                 5       B.A. (H) History          23     9     4     15     6      3        2          1
                 6       B.A. (H) Political        47     17  9       31     11     6        5          1
                         Science
                 7        B.A. (H) Sanskrit        16     6     3     11     3      2        2          0
                 8       B.A. (H) Sociology        23     9     4     15     6      3        2          1
                 9       B.Com. (Programme)        47     17  9       31     11     5        4          1
                 10      B.Com. (H)                31     11  6       21     9      4        3          1
                 11      B.Sc. Life Sciences       47     17  9       31     13     6        5          1
                 12      B.Sc. Physical Sciences   16     6     3     11     3      2        1          1
                         with Chemistry
                 13      B.Sc. Physical Sciences   15     6     3     11     4      2        2          0
                         with Computer Science
                 14      B.Sc. (H) Botany          16     6     3     11     3      2        1          1

                 15      B.Sc. (H) Chemistry       16     6     3     11     3      2        1          1
                 16      B.Sc. (H) Mathematics     20     7     4     13     5      2        1          1
                 17      B.Sc. (H) Physics         16     6     3     11     3      2        1          1
                 18      B.Sc. (H) Zoology         16     6     3     11     3      2        1          1
                 19      M.Sc. (Mathematics)       Reservation as per University/ UGC norms, 39
                 20      M.A. (Political Science)   Reservation as per University/ UGC norms, 39

               * Supernumerary Seats



                All applicants must register through the University of Delhi online admissions portal
                                                    https://ug.du.ac.in
                 All undergraduate admissions for 2021-22 will be administered only through this
                                                           portal.
                                  There will be no offline admission for any applicant.




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 5]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                  SUBJECT COMBINATIONS FOR B.A. (PROGRAMME) AND DISTRIBUTION OF SEATS

                S. No.   DSC-IA                         DSC-IB                             No. of Students
                1       Political Science               History                            33
                2       Political Science               Sociology                          30
                3       Political Science               Hindi Discipline                   26
                4       Political Science               Sanskrit                           11
                5       Political Science               Punjabi Discipline                 8
                6       History                         Hindi Discipline                   14
                7       History                         Punjabi Discipline                 8
                8       History                         Sanskrit                           5
                9       Sociology                       English Discipline                 26
                10      Economics                       English Discipline                 25
                11      Economics                       Mathematics                        10
                12      Economics                       Computer Applications              20
                13      Computer Applications           Mathematics                        15


                ADMISSION CRITERIA

               QUALIFICATION
               Qualifying  examination  for  the  purpose  of  admission  to  the  first  year  of  undergraduate
               courses  offered  by  the  University  of  Delhi  shall  be  Senior  Secondary  School  Certificate
               Examination  (Class  XII)  of  the  Central  Board  of  Secondary  Education  or  an  examination
               recognized as equivalent thereto.
               The applicants seeking admission to the undergraduate courses offered by the University
               should have passed the qualifying examination obtaining minimum marks as specified for
               each of the courses in subsequent sections.
               The applicant should have passed individually in each subject required (including practicals,
               if any) for calculating merit and eligibility to the course they seek admission in.

               Equivalence Criteria
               The applications for admission to the undergraduate courses in the College in respect of
               applicants  belonging  to  the  Examining  bodies  of  Boards/  Universities  recognized/
               accredited by the Association of Indian University/ University Grants Commission/ Ministry
               of Human Resource Development shall be considered by the College/ Department in terms
               of the following recommendations.
               Senior School Certificate of various Boards recognized by Association of Indian Universities/
               Central  Board  of  Secondary  Education  is  considered  as  equivalent  to  the  Senior  School
               Certificate of Central Board for the purposes of eligibility to various undergraduate courses.
               Students who pass various Degree/ School Examination of Foreign Universities/ Boards as
               have already been approved by the Equivalence Committee, from time to time, be considered
               eligible as a matter of routine.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 6]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                  Note: 1) Students passing the eleven-year school examination will not be eligible for
                  admission to any undergraduate course in the College.
                  2) Applicants with “compartment” results are not eligible to apply.
                  3) Applicants  with  gap year(s)  will  not  be  at  any  disadvantage  for  the  purpose  of
                  admission to undergraduate courses.
                  4) Admission in any course shall not be granted on the basis of projected scores issued
                  by any Board/ School.


               M.A. ADMISSION
               Students who wish to join post-graduate courses must submit their application to the College
               on prescribed forms after registration in South Campus on the dates to be notified by the
               University of Delhi. Names of candidates accepted for admission to M.A. will appear in the
               list of South Campus office at Benito Juarez Marg, Dhaula Kuan, New Delhi- 110021.


                ADMISSION PROCEDURE


                     The admission process for Merit based UG admission will be uploaded on the website
                       of the University of Delhi. All aspirants must register online as per the procedure and
                       schedule that will be notified on the University of Delhi website.
                     Only eligible applicants who have registered online through the University portal can
                       be considered for admission.
                     Applicants will be required to appear in person at the University of Delhi only at the
                       very end of the admission process, for verification of certificates as per the schedule
                       to be announced by the University/ College.
                     All other admission procedures are to be completed by the applicant using the unique
                       login  ID  they  create  on  the  Delhi  University  Undergraduate  admissions  portal
                       (Registration process to be announced on the University website).


                   For  all  applicants  seeking  admission  to  the  I year  of  B.A.  (Hons.)/  B.A.  (Prog.)/  B.Sc.
                   (Hons)/ B.Sc. (Prog.)/ B.Com. (Hons.)/ B.Com. (Prog.):
                     The marks entered by the applicant will serve as the basis for computing the total
                       marks  for  course-specific  combinations  of  'Best  Four'  Subjects  for  admission  in
                       courses  through  the  faculties  of  Arts,  Commerce,  Mathematical  Sciences,  Social
                       Sciences,  and  Humanities,  and  'Three  Subjects'  for  admission  in  courses  under
                       faculties of Sciences and Applied Sciences. Please refer to List A, List B and additional
                       eligibility criteria in the following tables on next page.
                     All academic subjects may be treated as “elective.”
                     The  University may define any other  relevant  subjects as  academic/elective  for  a
                       particular course.






                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 7]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                     For admission to some courses, inclusion of any subject other than those from List A
                       and List B, may lead to a deduction of 2.5% per such subject in the aggregate of " Best
                       Four" percentage.
                     Where language subjects are permitted/included in course-specific eligibility/ merit
                       computations,  if  an  applicant  has  studied  elective  and  core  languages,  the
                       core/elective language subject will be treated as language, while elective language
                       can be considered as academic/elective subject.
                     For admission to BA (Hons.) courses, “Best Four” may include a maximum of two
                       language subjects, in which one core language and one elective language subject, or
                       two elective language subjects (from List A) may be included.
                     For admission to Honours in any language course, advantage of 2% in the ‘Best Four’
                       percentage will be given to those applicants who have studied that particular elective
                       language. In some cases (Honours courses in some languages) a deduction of 5% is
                       applicable  where  the  applicant  has  not  studied  the  language  in  the  qualifying
                       examination.
                     For  admission  to  B.A  (Hons)  courses  offered  by  the  Faculty  of  Social  Sciences,  a
                       deduction of 2.5% is applicable where the applicant has not studied the concerned
                       subject in which admission is sought.
                     For admission to B.Com courses, a deduction of 1% is applicable if certain subjects
                       are not included in the calculation.
                     For admission to some B.Sc/ B.Voc courses, an advantage/ relaxation (varies from
                       course to course) is given to applicants who have studied particular subjects in the
                       qualifying examination.
                     Applicants should have passed theory and practical separately. Any paper with both
                       theory and practical component will be considered only in the ratio 70 (theory): 30
                       (practical) if the theory component of the paper is less than 70%.
                     “Internal Assessment” marks mentioned in the marksheet will not be used for any
                       calculations.

















                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 8]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               LIST- A: LANGUAGE SUBJECTS

                                                  List A1                                        List A2

                Assamese        Gujarati Core/  Maithili Core/  Odia Core/    Tamil Core/    Arabic Core/
                Core/           Gujarati       Maithili      Odia Elective    Tamil Elective  Arabic Elective
                Assamese        Elective       Elective
                Elective
                Bengali Core/  Hindi Core/     Malayalam     Punjabi Core/    Telegu Core/   French Core/
                Bengali         Hindi Elective  Core/        Punjabi Elective  Telegu Elective  French Elective
                Elective                       Malayalam
                                               Elective
                Bodo Core/      Kannada Core/  Manipuri      Sanskrit Core/  Urdu Core/      German Core/
                Bodo Elective  Kannada         Core/         Sanskrit         Urdu Elective  German Elective
                                Elective       Manipuri      Elective
                                               Elective
                Dogri Core/     Kashmiri       Marathi Core/  Santhali Core/                 Italian Core/
                Dogri Elective  Core/          Marathi       Santhali                        Italian Elective
                                Kashmiri       Elective      Elective
                                Elective
                English Core/  Konkani Core/  Nepali Core/  Sindhi Core/                     Persian Core/
                English         Konkani        Nepali        Sindhi Elective                 Persian Elective
                Elective        Elective       Elective
                                                                                             Spanish Core/
                                                                                             Spanish Elective



               LIST- B: ELECTIVE SUBJECTS

                Accountancy                    Computer Science/              Mathematics
                                               Computer Applications/
                                               Informatics Practices
                Anthropology                   Economics                      Philosophy/ Logic and
                                                                              Philosophy
                Biology/Biochemistry/          Geography                      Physics
                Biotechnology
                Business Mathematics           Geology                        Political Science
                Chemistry                      History                        Psychology
                Civics                         Home Science                   Sociology
                Commerce/Business              Legal Studies                  Statistics
                Studies








                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 9]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                                 Additional Eligibility Criteria and Course-wise Combination of
                 Course
                                 Subjects
                                   An aggregate of 45% marks in the qualifying examination.
                                   The applicant must have studied and passed English in the qualifying
                                   exam  and  should  include  English  for  calculation  of  ‘Best  Four’
                                   percentage.
                                   Merit  shall  be  determined  on  the  basis  of  ‘Best  Four’  featuring  one
                 B.A. (Hons.)      language  and  three  best  academic/elective  subjects  from  among  the
                 English           subjects in List A and List B.
                                   Inclusion of any subject other than those from List A and List B in the
                                   combination  of best three will lead to  a deduction  of 2.5% per such
                                   subject included in the aggregate ‘Best Four’ percentage.
                                   An advantage of 2% in the ‘Best Four’ percentage will be given to those
                                   applicants who have studied English as an elective subject (See List A).
                                   An aggregate of 45% marks in the qualifying examination.
                                   The  applicant  must  have  studied  and  passed  Mathematics  at  the
                                   qualifying examination for admission to B.A. (Honours) in Economics.
                                   The merit shall be determined on the basis of one language and three
                                   best academic/elective subjects as specified in List A and List B above.
                 B.A. (Hons.)      Out of three academic/elective subjects chosen above, one must be the
                 Economics         concerned  subject  in  which  the  admission  is  sought,  failing  which  a
                                   deduction  of  2.5%  will  be  imposed  on  the  aggregate  ‘Best  Four’
                                   percentage.
                                   Inclusion of any subject other than those given in Lists A and B in the
                                   ‘best three’ will lead to a deduction of 2.5% per subject on the aggregate
                                   of the Best Four.

                                   An aggregate of 45% marks in the qualifying examination.
                                   Merit shall be determined on the basis of one language and three best
                                   academic/elective subjects as specified in List A and List B.
                                   Inclusion of any subject other than those from List A and List B in the
                                   combination  of best three will lead to  a deduction  of 2.5% per such
                 B.A. (Hons.)      subject included in the aggregate ‘Best Four’ percentage.
                 History/          Out of three academic/elective subjects chosen above, one must be the
                 Political         concerned  subject  in  which  the  admission  is  sought,  failing  which  a
                 Science/          deduction  of  2.5%  will  be  imposed  on  the  aggregate  ‘Best  Four’
                 Sociology         percentage.

                                   Admission to B.A. (Hons.) Applied Psychology will be based on ‘Best
                                   Four’ percentage as in B.A. (Hons.) Psychology.
                                   Admission to B.A. (Hons.) Social Work and B.A. (Hons.) Philosophy will
                                   be based on ‘Best Four’ percentage including one language and three
                                   academic/elective subjects.





                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 10]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                                   An aggregate of 45% marks in the qualifying examination.
                                   Applicants securing 40% or more marks in the aggregate in and 50%
                                   marks  in  Hindi  in  the  qualifying  examination  are  also  eligible  for
                                   admission to the relevant Honours Course.
                                   Applicants who have passed the intermediate Examination of an Indian
                                   University/Board with at least 40% marks in the aggregate and also
                                   ‘Prabhakar in Hindi’ shall be eligible for admission.
                                   The  applicant  must  have  studied  and  passed  Hindi  in  the  qualifying
                 B.A. (Hons.)
                 Hindi             exam and should include Hindi for calculation of ‘Best Four’ percentage.
                                   Merit  shall  be  determined  on  the  basis  of  ‘Best  Four’  featuring  one
                                   language  and  three  best  academic/elective  subjects  from  among  the
                                   subjects in List A and List B.
                                   Inclusion of any subject other than those from List A and List B in the
                                   combination  of best three will lead to  a deduction  of 2.5% per such
                                   subject included in the aggregate ‘Best Four’ percentage.
                                   An advantage of 2% in the ‘Best Four’ percentage will be given to those
                                   applicants who have studied Hindi as an elective subject (See List A).
                                  An aggregate of 45% marks in the qualifying examination.
                                  Applicants  securing  40%  marks  in  the  aggregate  and  50%  marks  in
                                   Sanskrit are also eligible.
                                  Applicants who have passed the intermediate Examination of an Indian
                                   University/Board with at least 40% marks in the aggregate and also the
                                   following  examination  shall  be  eligible  for  admission:  Shastri  in
                                   Sanskrit.
                                  The merit shall be determined on the basis of one language and three
                 B.A. (Hons.)      best academic/elective subjects from List A and List B above.
                 Sanskrit         Inclusion of any subject other than those from List A and List B in the
                                   combination  of best three will lead to a  deduction of 2.5% per such
                                   subject included in the aggregate ‘Best Four’ percentage.
                                  Advantage of 2% will be given in the aggregate ‘Best Four’ percentage
                                   to those applicants who have studied Sanskrit elective language.
                                  In case the applicant has not studied Sanskrit at qualifying examination
                                   level  and  is  seeking  admission  to  an  Honours  course  in  Sanskrit,
                                   deduction of 5% will be imposed on ‘Best Four’ aggregate percentage.












                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 11]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




            Course         Additional Eligibility Criteria and Course-wise Combination of Subjects
                             An aggregate of 40% marks in the qualifying examination.

                             The  merit  shall  be  determined  on  the  basis  of  one  language  (core/  elective/
                              functional) and three best academic/ elective subjects as specified in List A and
            B.A. (Prog.)      List B above may be chosen.
            (Discipline
            Subject-         One  non-listed  subject  (besides  the  elective  subjects  in Lists  A  and B)  can  be
            based             included in calculation of ‘Best Four’ without any deduction.
            Admission
            Criteria)
                             If more than one non-listed subject is included for calculation of ‘Best Four’, a
                              deduction of 2.5% each in ‘Best Four’ may be levied in addition to deduction due
                              to change of stream, if any.

            B.Com.           An aggregate of 45% marks in the qualifying examination.
            (Hons.)          The  applicant  must  have  studied  and  passed  Mathematics/Business
                              Mathematics/  equivalent  paper  as  specified  in  Annexure  X  at  the  qualifying
                              examination for admission to B. Com. (Hons.).
                             Selection shall be made on the basis of marks obtained in qualifying examination
                              including one language and three best subjects as per the following:
                            o An aggregate of 45% or more in English/Hindi and combination of best three
                              among  the  following  subjects:  Mathematics,  Accountancy,  Economics  and
                              Business Studies/ Commerce.
                            o Inclusion  of  any  subject  from  List  B  other  than  mentioned  above  in  the
                              combination  of  best  three  will  lead  to  a  deduction  of  1%  per  subject  on  the
                              aggregate.
                             Inclusion of any subject other than those in Lists A and B in the combination of
                              best three will lead to a deduction of 2.5% per subject on the aggregate of the ‘Best
                              Four’.
            B.Com.           An aggregate of 40% marks in the qualifying examination.
            (Prog.)          Selection shall be made on the basis of marks obtained in qualifying examination
                              including one language and three best subjects as per the following:
                            o An aggregate of 40% or more in English/Hindi and combination of the best three
                              from among the following subjects: Mathematics, Accountancy, Economics and
                              Business Studies/ Commerce.
                            o Inclusion  of  any  subject  from  List  B  other  than  mentioned  above  in  the
                              combination  of  best  three  will  lead  to  a  deduction  of  1%  per  subject  on  the
                              aggregate.
                             Inclusion of any subject other than those in Lists A and B in the combination of
                              best three will lead to a deduction of 2.5% per subject on the aggregate of the ‘Best
                              Four’.




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 12]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                  Course            Additional Eligibility Criteria and Course-wise Combination of
                                    Subjects
                 B.Sc. (Hons.)       50%  marks  in  Mathematics  and  an  aggregate  of  45%  marks  in  the
                 Mathematics          qualifying examination.
                                     Merit shall be determined on the basis of one language, Mathematics
                                      and two best academic/ elective subjects as specified in List A and List
                                      B above.
                 B.Sc. (Hons.)       55% or more marks in the aggregate of Physics, Chemistry, Biology/
                 Botany/              Biotechnology (Practical & Theory together) and 50% or more marks
                 Zoology              in one compulsory language i.e. English.
                                     Merit  will  be  calculated  based  on  aggregate  percentage  in  Physics,
                                      Chemistry, Biology/ Biotechnology.
                 B.Sc. (Hons.)       55%  or  more  marks  in  the  aggregate  of  Physics,  Chemistry  and
                 Chemistry/           Mathematics and 50% or more marks in one compulsory language.
                 Physics             Merit will be calculated based on aggregate percentage in Physics,
                                      Chemistry and Mathematics.

                 B. Sc. (Prog.)      45% or more marks in the aggregate of Physics, Chemistry/ Computer
                 Physical             Science, Mathematics (Practical & Theory together) and passing in one
                 Science with         compulsory language (i.e. English).
                 Chemistry                                              OR

                 B.Sc. (Prog.)      45% or more marks in the aggregate of Physics, Chemistry/ Computer
                 Physical             Science, Mathematics (Practical & Theory together) and 40% in one
                 Science with         compulsory language.
                 Computer            Merit  will  be  calculated  based  on  aggregate  percentage  in  Physics,
                 Science              Chemistry/ Computer Science, Mathematics.

                 B.Sc. (Prog.)       45% or more marks in the aggregate of Physics, Chemistry, Biology/
                 Life Science         Biotechnology (Practical & Theory together) and passing in one
                                      compulsory language (i.e. English).
                                                                        OR
                                    45% or more marks in the aggregate of Physics, Chemistry, Biology/
                                      Biotechnology and 40% in one compulsory language.
                                     Merit will be calculated based on aggregate percentage in Physics,
                                      Chemistry, Biology/ Biotechnology.





                For any queries regarding admission in the College, contact: office@maitreyi.du.ac.in




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 13]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               Grade Conversion
               [As  per  AC  Resolution  No.  319,  Dt.  22.3.1976]  Formula/  equivalence  of  the  grade  point
               average awarded in Cambridge School Certificate/ Overseas/ African G.C.E./ Examination
               School Certificate Examination and/or XII Grade Examination of American Embassy School,
               New  Delhi  with  the  percentage  of  marks  as  are  awarded  in  the  Higher  Secondary
               Examination of the Central Board of Secondary Education, New Delhi, for the purpose of
               admission to different courses in the University of Delhi.



                   Grade   Min. % of Each Grade             Grade       Mean Resultant Percentage
                   1        90                              A           90
                   2        75                              B           75
                   3        66                              C           60
                   4        61                              D           40
                   5        57                              E           30
                   6        51                              F           Fail
                   7        47
                   8        40
                   9        Fail





                                 Admission to IB Students (IB Grade to Marks Scheme)

                             Grade      Indian Equivalent Marks
                             7          96-100                    Midpoint 98
                             6          83-95                     Midpoint 89
                             5          70-82                     Midpoint 76
                             4          56-69                     Midpoint 62.5
                             3          41-55                     Midpoint 48
                             2          21-40                     Midpoint 30.5
                             1          1-20                      Midpoint 10.5











                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 14]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               CERTIFICATES REQUIRED FOR ADMISSION

               The applicants shall be required to upload copies of the following certificates/documents at
               the  time  of  registration  and  produce  the  documents  in  original  at  the  time  of  physical
               verification at the end of the admissions process:
                   1.  Class X Certificate (Mark-sheet or certificate) indicating date of birth and parents’
                       names.     (The     names      of    applicants    claiming     reservation     under
                       SC/ST/OBC/EWS/CW/KM  must  match  with  the  names  that  appear  on  the
                       corresponding reservation certificates; similarly their parents’ names must match in
                       both sets of certificates).
                   2.  Class XII Marksheet.
                   3.  SC/ST/OBC/EWS/CW/KM Certificate (in the name of the Applicant) issued by the
                       competent  authority.  (The  names  of  applicants  claiming  reservation  under
                       SC/ST/OBC/EWS/CW/KM  must  match  with  the  names  that  appear  on  their
                       corresponding School  Board qualifying certificates; similarly their parents’ names
                       must match in both sets of certificates).
                   4.  OBC (Non-Creamy Layer) Certificate  (in the name of the  Applicant) issued by the
                       competent  authority,  and  wherein  the  caste  is  in  the  OBC  central  list  issued  by
                       http://ncbc.nic.in. (The name of the applicant claiming reservation under OBC (Non-
                       Creamy  Layer)  must  match  with  the  applicant’s  name  as  it  appears  on  their
                       corresponding School  Board qualifying certificates; similarly their parents’ names
                       must match in both sets of certificates). Income certificate for the financial year 2020-
                       21, dated on or after March 31, 2021, as stipulated, will be required.
                   5.  EWS  Certificate  from  competent  authority  certifying  the  applicant  can  claim
                       reservation under this category. (The names of applicants claiming reservation under
                       this category must match with the names that appear on their corresponding School
                       Board qualifying certificates; similarly their parents’ names must match in both sets
                       of certificates). Income certificate for the financial year 2020-21, dated on or after
                       March 31, 2021, as stipulated, will be required.
                   6.  Any applicants claiming admission through ECA/Sports categories must upload self-
                       attested copies of the requisite certificates/produce the relevant required certificates
                       when sought as stipulated in Section 6 of this Bulletin of Information.

               Applicants shall be responsible for the quality and authenticity of the images they
               upload at the time of registration. Applicants must take care to ensure that uploads
               are  authentic  and  accurate.  Applicants  will  be  responsible  for  production  of
               documents as sought. All certificates/ documents will be returned to the applicant by
               the College/ Department upon completion of any physical verification that may be
               required at a later stage.
               If the applicants do not have recent/ valid EWS/ OBC (Non-Creamy Layer)/ SC or ST Caste/
               Tribe certificate at the time of Registration, the applicant may upload the acknowledgement
               slip of application for the certificate. However, at the time of admission, the applicant will
               have to produce his/ her recent/ valid original EWS/ OBC (Non-Creamy Layer)/ SC/ ST
               certificate.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 15]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               RESERVATION OF SEATS

               In each course, seats are reserved as per following details:

                 (i)      Scheduled Caste                              15%         Interchangeable if
                 (ii)     Scheduled Tribe                              7.5%        necessary
                 (iii)    OBC (Non Creamy Layer)                       27%
                 (iv)     Economically Weaker Section (EWS)            10%
                 (v)      Persons with Disability (PwD)                5%
                 (vi)     Widows/  Children of  Military Personnel  5%
                          killed in war (CW)
                 (vii)    Foreign Students                             5%
               For  admission  to  the  categories  (iv),  (v),  (vi)  and  (vii)  above,  kindly  refer  to  University
               admission bulletin of information 2021-22.

               FOREIGN STUDENTS
               Foreign students who wish to join College must satisfy the course and age requirements
               according to the University rules. All foreign students, including those who have completed
               their schooling from an Indian Board may be treated as Foreign students for the purpose of
               their registration/ admission in the College and they may be considered for admission under
               5% quota prescribed for the foreign students. No foreign student shall be admitted to the
               College without the prior approval from the Deputy Dean (foreign students) University of
               Delhi. The foreign applicants seeking admission to undergraduate programmes should apply
               online through foreign students' registry portal http://fsr.du.ac.in and can contact Deputy
               Dean (Foreign Students' Registry), Conference Centre, University of Delhi-110007.


               RELAXATIONS IN COURSE-SPECIFIC ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA FOR THE ADMISSION OF
               CANDIDATES UNDER SC, ST, OBC, EWS AND  PwD CATEGORIES AS PER UNIVERSITY
               GUIDELINES
                   1.  Relaxation to the extent of 5% in the minimum marks shall be given to the applicants
                       belonging to SC and ST to determine their eligibility and merit for admission to the
                       course concerned. In case, after giving 5% relaxation, the reserved seats still remain
                       vacant, further relaxation would be given to the extent required in order to fill all the
                       reserved seats in the course concerned. Eligibility in such cases is pass percentage.
                   2.  The OBC applicants shall be given a relaxation of 10% in the minimum eligibility
                       marks of the said course and for the admission entrance test a relaxation of 10% of
                       the minimum eligibility marks prescribed for General/ UR Category applicants.
                   3.  It is reiterated that only those OBC candidates who belong to the 'Non-Creamy Layer'
                       and whose caste appear in the Central List of the OBCs only shall be eligible to be
                       considered for admission under the OBC category.
                   4.  College has reserved 10% seats for admission for the Economically Weaker Sections
                       (EWSs) category from this Academic Year, 2021-22. The eligibility of such applicants
                       will  be  decided  on  the  basis  of  fulfilling  criteria  and  subject  to  submission  of
                       documents, issued by the competent authority, in the format provided in the bulletin


                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 16]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                       of  information  from  University  of  Delhi.  For  further  details  applicants  can  visit:
                       http://www.du.ac.in/du/uploads/Notifications/04042019-NotificationEWS. Pdf
                   5.  PwD  applicants  shall  be  given  a  relaxation  in  the  course-specific  eligibility  in  the
                       qualifying examination and in the admission entrance test to the extent of 5%, till
                       seats are filled.
                   6.  Eligibility  Criteria  for  merit-based  admissions  under  the  EWS  category  shall  be
                       identical to that of UR category.
                   7.  Candidates seeking admission under SC/ ST/ OBC/ EWS/ PwD category should have
                       certificates in their own name only.

               GUIDELINES FOR SPORTS AND ECA ADMISSIONS
                   1.  The admission under the Sports and ECA category is centralized as per the University
                       guidelines available in the University Bulletin of Information.
                   2.  The number of seats will not exceed 5% for Sports/ ECA quota.
                   3.  An applicant being selected in the final list does not guarantee admission. Admission
                       is subject to the availability of seats in a course/ College.
                   4.  Due to the unprecedented situation that has emerged because of COVID -19, the
                       trials will be held as per the prevailing public health guidelines at the time of
                       admission. In case the situation does not allow the physical presence of the
                       candidates, the University shall announce its policy accordingly.
                   5.  Not  more  than  15%  concession  in  academic  merit  vis-a-vis  unreserved  category
                       applicants  (for  the  last  relevant  cut-off)  may  be  given  for  admission  to  a  specific
                       course subject to course-specific eligibility criteria. Admissions under ECA/Sports
                       category will only be allowed to applicants satisfying the course-specific minimum
                       eligibility criteria.
                   6.  The selected students shall submit an undertaking at the time of admission stating
                       that the applicant will perform for the College and University, all the years, during
                       applicant's undergraduate programme of study.
                   7.  The applicant submitting false/ fake certificate will be debarred from admission to
                       any programme in any College for three years. If applicant seeks admission on the
                       basis of false/ fake certificates, not only admission will be cancelled, an FIR may also
                       be registered against her.
                   8.  The decision of ECA admission committee shall be final.







                   Note: Students staying in the PG or private hostels are required to submit their
                        present address with phone numbers and intimate the changes, if any.





                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 17]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                FEES AND OTHER CHARGES

                                                  A. GOVERNMENT FUND
                 Tuition Fee Rs. 15 per month                                                         180.00
                 Tuition Fee Rs. 18 per month for M.A.                                                216.00
                 Admission Fee                                                                           5.00
                 College Magazine Fee                                                                 100.00
                 Library and Reading Room Fee                                                         250.00
                 Identity Card Fee                                                                     50.00
                 Garden Fee                                                                           150.00
                 Science Annual Charges                                                                10.00
                 Water and Electricity Fee                                                            800.00
                 Total (for Science students)                                                       1545.00
                 Total (for other students)                                                         1535.00
                 Total (For M.A./ M.Sc. students)                                                   1571.00
                                                   B. UNIVERSITY FUND
                 University Enrolment Fee (only for I Year students)                                  200.00
                 University Re-Enrolment Fee (for M.A./ M.Sc. I Year)                                 100.00
                 University Library Development Fund (Non-Refundable) (For M.A./ M.Sc. I              200.00
                 Year)
                 Cultural Council Fee                                                                    5.00
                 Sports Council Fee                                                                    50.00
                 NSS Fund                                                                              20.00
                 WUS-DUS Fund                                                                            2.00
                 University Development Fund                                                          600.00
                 Gender Sensitization Fee                                                                2.00
                 Total (for M.A/ M.Sc. students)                                                     979.00
                 Total (for all other students of I year)                                            879.00
                                                     C. COLLEGE FUND
                 College Caution Money                                                                500.00
                 Students Activities Fee                                                              900.00
                 Games Fee                                                                            600.00
                 Medical Inspection Fee                                                               150.00
                 Students Union Fee                                                                   100.00
                 Students Aid Fund                                                                       5.00
                 Development Fund                                                                     400.00
                 College Facility Fee                                                                 700.00
                 Building Development and Extension Fund                                              400.00
                 Science Lab. Facility Fee (for Science students only)                              1,400.00
                 Computer Lab. Fee {B.A. (Prog.) Computer Applications/ B.Sc. (Prog.)}                900.00
                 Maintenance Fee                                                                      400.00
                 Internal Assessment Fee                                                               50.00



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 18]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                  Gender Sensitization Fee                                                               8.00
                 Academic Society Fee                                                                 150.00
                 WUS-DUS Fund                                                                            3.00
                 Workshops/ Seminars/ Field Work                                                      200.00
                 Total for B.A. (Prog.)/ B.Com./ B.A. (Hons)                                       4,566.00
                 Total for B.Com. (Hons.)/ B.A. (Prog.) with Computer Applications                 5,466.00
                 Total for B.SC. (HONS.) Physics/ Chemistry/ Botany/ Zoology/ Maths                5,966.00
                 Total for B.Sc. (Prog.) Life Sciences/ Physical Sciences                          6,866.00
                 Total for M.A./ M.Sc. I Year                                                      5,066.00
                 University Library Security Deposit (Refundable) (for M.A./ M.Sc. I Year)            500.00
                 GRAND TOTAL B.A. (PROG.)/ B.COM. (PROG.)                                          6,980.00
                 GRAND TOTAL B.A. (PROG.) WITH COMPUTER APPLICATIONS                               7,880.00
                 GRAND TOTAL B.A. (HONS.) ALL COURSES                                              6,980.00
                 GRANTTOTALB.COM. (HONS.)                                                          7,880.00
                 GRAND TOTAL B.SC. (PROG.) LIFE SCIENCES/ PHYSICAL SCIENCES                        9,290.00
                 GRAND  TOTAL  B.SC.  (HONS.)  PHYSICS/  CHEMISTRY/  BOTANY/                       8,390.00
                 ZOOLOGY/ MATHS
                 GRAND TOTAL M.A./ M.SC. I YEAR                                                    7,616.00

                 Note: 1) University examination fee will be charged later on as and when required.
                 2) Students are required to give the bank account details only on her name carefully. The
                 final and sole responsibility of cross-checking the account number, bank IFSC code and
                 every other detail lies with the student, and the college will not be held responsible for any
                 accidental transfer of fees refund amount to an unintended recipient.


               RE-ADMISSION
               (a) A student of the University having failed to pass any examination of the University will
               be  registered  as  an  ex-  student  for  re-appearing  in  the  said  examination  subject  to  the
               conditions  laid  down  under  the  regulations  of  the  University  relating  to  conditions  of
               admission to University examinations.
               (b) A student of the University who was not allowed to appear in the examinations due to
               shortage of attendance will be re-admitted to the class he/she studied last in his College/
               Department, within the prescribed period of registration.
               (c) A student, whose name is removed from the College rolls for non-payment of fees or for
               any other reason, may be permitted re-admission at the discretion  of the Principal on a
               written  request  on  the  prescribed  form  obtainable  from  the  College  cashier.  Such  re-
               admission  shall  be  on  payment  of  re-admission  fee,  arrears  of  tuition  fee  and  fines
               immediately after the permission is granted.



                  Note: All students must read and abide by the core values put forth by the College
                                              in "Code of Conduct" booklet.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 19]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                TERMS OF PAYMENT
               Dates and mode of payment of fees and other dues by students are put up on the College
               notice board from time to time. If a student fails to pay her dues by the last specified date,
               she shall be fined at the rate of Rs.1 for each day of delay up to the last working day of the
               month and if she fails to pay her fees by the last day fixed, her name will be removed from
               the College rolls. Tuition fee for all the twelve months of an academic year is to be paid in
               one installment.

               REFUND OF FEES
               When a student withdraws her name from the College rolls, fees and other dues, if any, will
               be  refunded  in  the  month  of  October  in  accordance  with  the  University  rules  only  after
               submission of an application together with a clearance slip duly completed by the student
               concerned after the withdrawal.

               REFUND OF SECURITY DEPOSIT/ CAUTION MONEY
               Security deposits are refundable, but payment will be made only on application within one
               year  from  the  date  of  withdrawal  of  the  student  from  the  rolls  of  the  College  and  after
               deducting the cost of breakage, loss of books and outstanding NCC/ Sports/ NSS dues, if any.
               If the amount of Caution Money is not withdrawn/ claimed within one year of the student
               leaving the College, it shall lapse. The refund will be made to the account through NEFT only.

               Rules for Refund of Fee on Account of Withdrawal/ Cancellation of Admission:
                  S. No.   Reasons for seeking refund                      Quantum of fee to be refunded
                          When  a  student  applies  for  withdrawal  of
                  1.                                                       Full fee after deduction of Rs. 1000
                          admission up to last date of admission
                          When admission is made inadvertently due to
                  2.      error/  omission/  commission  on  the  part  of  Full fee
                          the University/ College
                          When  cancellation  of  admission  is  due  to
                          concealment/ falsification of facts, submission
                  3.      of  false/  fake  certificates(s),  providing  No fee will be refunded
                          misleading information by the student or for
                          any error/ mistake on the part of the student
                          When  a  student  of  self-financing  course
                  4.      applies  for  withdrawal  of  admission  on  or  Full fee after deduction of Rs. 1000
                          before the last date of admission
                          In  case  a  student  after  his/  her  admission
                  5.      expires within  one  month of the  last date  of  Full fee will be refunded to parents
                          admission


                  Note: 1) For refund of fees contact: accounts@maitreyi.du.ac.in
                  2) Amount of refunded fee will be credited to the student's bank account as per the
                  bank account details provided by the student in the withdrawal form. No cheque/
                  cash will be issued.

                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 20]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               FEE CONCESSION AND STIPENDS
               The College awards fee concession to deserving and meritorious students to the extent of
               20% of the total fees collected during the year according to rules. Applications on prescribed
               form are  to  be  submitted to  the  account section  by 31st  August, 2021. The  College also
               provides exemption of tuition fee and admission fee to all Scheduled Caste/ Tribe students
               whose parents' income is below taxable limit, on production of a certificate fulfilling the
               necessary conditions.

               FREESHIP
                   1.  The College provides freeship to students whose parental income does not exceed Rs.
                       15,000 per month.
                   2.  The total amount granted to each such student is Rs. 380 per annum which includes
                       basic tuition fees of Rs. 180 and development fee of Rs. 200.
                   3.  Freeship is open to students of all categories i.e. General/ SC/ ST/ OBC.
                   4.  Forms for freeship to be filled in the month of September can be obtained from the
                       College office.


                RULES OF DISCIPLINE AND ATTENDANCE
               Every student admitted to the College is required to maintain discipline and good conduct in
               and outside the College during the period of her stay in the College (ragging in any form is
               strictly prohibited). Violation of discipline rules and acts of ragging, sexual harassment etc.
               are punishable according to the following Ordinances of the University:
                     Ordinance XV-B: Discipline
                     Ordinance XV-C: Anti-ragging
                     Ordinance XV-D: Sexual harassment

               Ragging is strictly prohibited and will invite suspension from College. The College will adhere
               to guidelines issued by the Honorable Supreme Court in such matters. A copy each of the
               above ordinances will be made available to all students at the time of admission along with
               identity card. Students are required to read these rules carefully and ensure good conduct
               and behavior during their stay in the  College. Any ragging incident may immediately be
               reported to students' union office bearers, faculty advisors or the Principal.

               RULES OF ATTENDANCE
               1. According to the provisions of Ordinance VII of University of Delhi, it is compulsory for
               every student to attend at least 2/3  i.e. 66.66% of the Lectures, Practical and Tutorials/
                                                     rd
               Preceptorial  separately  held  every  semester.  A  student  who  is  short  of  attendance  in
               Lectures or Practical or Tutorials/ Preceptorial will not be ordinarily allowed to take the
               University examination.
               2. At the end of every month, the College will upload attendance of all students on the College
               website. The College shall not  be  liable  to intimate individually every student  about  her
               attendance record/ shortage from the concerned Teachers/ Teacher-in-charge.






                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 21]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               3. Students who fall ill should inform the College within a week of their illness and submit
               the medical certificate within 15 days of their rejoining after recovery from illness. Medical
               certificate after this period may not be accepted.
               4. Benefit of attendance of exclusion of not more than 1/3  of the number of Lectures/
                                                                              rd
               Practical/ Preceptorial on medical grounds or on grounds of active participation in cultural
               activities may be given to the students as per University rules subject to the approval of the
               College authorities.

                 The Time Table of all Undergraduate courses will be put up on the College website.

                EXAMINATION AND PROMOTION

                   1.  There are two components for evaluation:
                          a.  Internal Assessment (Continuous Evaluation)
                          b.  End-Semester Examination
                   2.  25% of the maximum marks in each paper are assigned for internal assessment and
                       remaining 75% marks are for the end-semester examination.
                   3.  The internal assessment is based on tutorial work/ class preceptorial/ assignment
                       and attendance. The respective weightage being 10%, 10% and 5% respectively.
                   4.  The internal assessment marks will be shown separately in the Marksheet issued by
                       the University and these marks will be added to the semester examination marks for
                       determining the division obtained by the student.
                   5.  There will be a University examination at the end of each semester.
                   6.  Science  students  will  be  evaluated  continuously  throughout  the  semester  besides
                       their end-semester exam both for Theory and Practical.
                   7.  No  concession  in  attendance  is  given  to  a  student  joining  a  course  late  or  being
                       transferred to a course.
                   8.  Students falling short of attendance are liable to be detained and not allowed to take
                       the final examination. Minimum attendance required is 66.66%.
                   9.  The students shall fill the examination form for a particular semester after payment
                       of the prescribed examination fee before the examination schedule.

                SCHOLARSHIPS AND PRIZES

               Delhi University holds a competitive examination in the month of October each year for the
               award of All India Entrance Scholarship of Rs. 250 per month or as per University guidelines
               tenable for three years to students of B.A. (Hons.) and B.Sc. (Hons.). Desirous students may
               apply  along  with  an  examination  fee  of  Rs.  50  on  the  prescribed  forms  available  at  the
               Examination  Branch-VII  (i)  of  the  University  of  Delhi.  Applicants  may  enquire  from  the
               College office for any other details.
               Undergraduate Science Meritorious Award is given to students who secure highest marks in
               B.Sc. (Hons.) Physics, Chemistry, Botany and Zoology, by the University.
               Note: Parents are requested to regularly check attendance of their ward at the beginning of
               every month at www.maitreyi.du.ac.in


                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 22]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               SCHOLARSHIP TO SC/ ST STUDENTS
               Candidates belonging to Scheduled Castes/ Tribes are awarded scholarships by the states to
               which they belong. Such students are advised to obtain application forms from the accounts
               section immediately after their admission and submit the same duly completed along with
               the required certificates on or before 20  August, 2021. Claims for scholarship by a student
                                                        th
               will  be  entertained  only  if  she  submits  her  application  on  time.  The  continuance  of  any
               Freeship,  Scholarship  or  Grant  of  other  privileges  depends  on  satisfactory  academic
               progress, regular attendance, discipline and good conduct. Every stipend holder has to abide
               by the College rules and regulations.

               SCHOLARSHIP TO PwD STUDENTS
               PwD  students  who  are  getting  fellowships/  financial  assistance  shall  be  exempted  from
               payment of fees/ charges/ mess fees subject to the following conditions.
                  Value of Fellowship                               Exemption of Fees Waiver etc.
                  Up to Rs. 3000 per month                          Fees waiver + 50% Mess Subsidy
                  Rs. 3001 to 8000 per month                        Fees waiver but no Mess Subsidy
                  Rs. 8001 and above per month                      No fees waiver and no Hostel Subsidy

               Note:  All  admitted  SC/  ST,  OBC,  EWS,  PwD  students  in  College  who  are  eligible  for
               fellowships should submit their scholarship forms to the requisite office by February for
               timely processing.

               ACADEMIC PRIZES
                   1.  Prizes  are awarded to  the  College topper in each course,  each year, provided  the
                       aggregate is 55% or above.
                   2.  Dr. Radha Sai Ram Memorial Award to the Best Student of Chemistry (Hons.) I year.
                   3.  Smt. Durga Devi Memorial Prize to the Best Student of Chemistry (Hons.) II year.
                   4.  Dr. Savita M Datta Memorial Prize of Rs. 5000 each, to the Best student of Physics
                       (Hons.), all three years.
                   5.  Dr. Sita Srivastava Memorial Award of Rs. 11000 along with trophy to the best all-
                       rounder student from II or III year.
                   6.  Prof. B.L. Verma Memorial Scholarship of Rs. 3000 for needy students (Annual Fees
                       Waiver).
                   7.  Late Smt. Lajwanti Chawla and Late Shri Nand Lal Chawla Memorial Scholarship of
                       Rs. 1100 each, for the best students from each of the I, II and III year of Hindi (Hons.),
                       and B.A. (Prog.).
                   8.  Late Raj Kumar Kochhar and Late Smt. Dr. Pushpa Kochhar Awards as: ‘Pushpanjali
                       Award’, a Meritorious Scholarship Award of Rs. 5000 each for the first and second
                       position holders of B.A. (Hons.) all three years; ‘Pushpraj Award’, Industry Incubation
                       Financial Support Award of Rs. 40,000, for Incubation Centre of the College; ‘Rajshree
                       Award’ of Rs. 3000 each for 10 needy students.
                   9.  Shri Ashwani Wadhwa Scholarship, of Rs. 5000 each for 10 needy students.
                   10. Late Sh JP Gupta Memorial Scholarship of Rs. 2000 each for Excellence in Zoology/
                       Life Sciences for I and II position holders in Zoology Hons and Life Sciences.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 23]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               SPORTS SCHOLARSHIP
               Scholarships and Freeship are given on the basis of performance and achievements in sports.

               OTHERS
               INSPIRE Scholarship for Higher Education (SHE) is a scholarship programme implemented
               by  the  Department  of  Science  and  Technology  (DST),  Government  of  India,  for  Science
               students. More details can be found at http://www.inspire-dst.gov.in/scholarship.html
               In  addition,  many  scholarships  are  being  given  by  the  Central  Government.  Interested
               students  can  visit  the  National  Scholarship  Portal,  https://scholarships.gov.in  for  more
               details.


                ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES

               ACADEMIC ASSOCIATIONS
               Each  department  of  the  College  runs  its  own  academic  association.  Through  these
               associations, classroom teaching is supplemented with seminars, workshops, exhibitions,
               debates, educational excursions, fieldwork and lectures given by eminent persons.

               AVGAAHAN- Annual Interdisciplinary Fest
               Avgaahan is an interdisciplinary academic fest, which aims to provide its participants with
               the opportunity to immerse into and investigate various disciplines through innovative and
               intellectually stimulating activities. It is a unique attempt undertaken by all departments of
               Maitreyi College to bridge the distance between various disciplines using ‘technology’. It is
               open to all national and international undergraduate students. In its second year “Avgaahan
               2021”, all competitions were organized in online mode to maximize student outreach and
               encourage higher participation of students across the globe. It included competitions like e-
               poster making, creative writing, case studies, coding, photo essays, quiz, and debate etc. The
               phenomenal  response  of  the  students  was  evident  in  the  scores  of  registration  and
               enthusiastic participation from National and International Universities.

               CENTRE FOR RESEARCH
               Since its inception in the year 2019 under the aegis of Maitreyi Research and Incubation
               Centre, giant strides have been taken by the Centre for Research to achieve its objective of
               promoting a research friendly environment in the college and to provide opportunities to
               students and faculty to delve into research questions. In the academic year 2020-2021, 53
               projects that were carried out under the Summer Internship Programme, which involved 66
               faculty members and 155 students. The theme of the Summer Internship Programme 2020-
               2021 was ‘COVID-19: Impact and implications'. All the projects were carried out in online
               mode. A new venture, “Annual Research Projects” was initiated from January, 2020, by the
               Centre for Research keeping in mind the enthusiasm and zeal shown by faculty and students
               alike for pursuing research activities throughout the year. This year 13 projects are being
               funded by the Centre for Research under this scheme.
               The  Centre  for  Research  publishes  a  biannual  peer-reviewed  multidisciplinary  e-journal
               'Vantage: Journal of Thematic Analysis'. The journal publishes original research papers as
               well as review papers, book reviews, perspectives, research communications and invited


                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 24]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               articles. The aim of the journal is to publish articles that contribute significantly to the body
               of knowledge on a specific theme. The theme for the April 2021 issue was 'Covid-19, Impact,
               Implications and Path Ahead'.

               EDUCATIONAL EXCURSIONS
               To promote learning outside the classroom, College initiated the practice of conducting One-
               day Educational Excursions which were organized individually by all departments. During
               the mid-semester break, approximately 1500 students benefited from these excursions as
               they learnt industrial practices and witnessed the application of their respective educational
               curricula.

               SHORT-TERM/ADD-ON COURSES
               Maitreyi strives to provide its students with a firm knowledge base and unique skills so that
               each one can create her own special niche in any area of work. Skill training leads to overall
               enhancement of employability, which is the need of the hour. The classes of various skill
               based short-term courses are held in the College campus and 6 hours/week is required by
               most  courses.  Classes  are  scheduled  after  regular  teaching  hours  (Friday  and  Saturday;
               2:30pm–5:30pm).  Fee  is  different  for  different  courses.  This  year  the  following  add  on
               courses are being offered:

                 S. NO.   COURSE             DURATION       AFFILIATION            ELIGIBILITY
                                                            Department of
                                                            Germanic and
                          French-                           Romance Studies        Registered in any UG
                 1.                          One year
                          Certificate                       (DGRS),                course
                                                            University of
                                                            Delhi (DU)
                          French-                                                  Should have completed
                 2.                          One year       DGRS, DU
                          Diploma                                                  Certificate course
                          Spanish-                                                 Registered in any UG
                 3.                          One year       DGRS, DU
                          Certificate                                              course
                          Spanish-                                                 Should have completed
                 4.                          One year       DGRS, DU
                          Diploma                                                  Certificate course
                          Spanish-                                                 Should have completed
                 5.       Advanced           One year       DGRS, DU               Certificate and Diploma
                          Diploma                                                  course
                          Metagenomics
                 6.       and                One  to  six   PhixGen                Registered in any UG
                                                                                   course
                                             weeks
                          Bioinformatics
                          English to Hindi                                         Registered in any UG
                 7.                          3 months       Maitreyi College
                          Translation                                              course



                      Note: For further queries, please write to shortterm.maitreyi@gmail.com


                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 25]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

               NCC/ NSS
               College maintains three companies of NCC, attached with 3 DGBn and has 152 cadets on roll
               allotted vacancy. Cadets are actively associated with various projects in College, and University.
               With the motto of “No  me but  you”, the NSS unit of Maitreyi College strives to reach out to
               underprivileged sections of society and use the platform to work towards social upliftment. From
               volunteering for blood donation camp to help Covid patients to participating in tree plantation
               drives, our volunteers have always strived hard to help the ones in need. Collaborating with
               NGOs, orphanages, old age homes to reach out to the ones in need has been our top most priority.
               NSS Maitreyi, in collaboration with ‘SAHAJA YOGA’, also successfully conducted a 10 days short
               term certificate course, workshop & training programme with participants from all over India,
               with the theme, ‘Balancing Body, Mind & Soul’. The overall objective of the course was to enhance
               concentration, productivity and harmonise energies for balanced professional and personal life
               to overcome the stressful condition of Covid-19. In addition, NSS unit has also started AAPKI
               MAITREYI, an education initiative wherein online classes were arranged for students from Class
               1 to 5 to make children engaged during this period with some exciting activities through virtual
               classes with the available resources, and DHYAN INITIATIVE, meditation classes arranged for all
               age groups free of cost.

               ENACTUS
               Enactus is a global student run organization that aims at uplifting the underprivileged section of
               the society through social entrepreneurship. The team participates in various workshops and
               competitions  organised  by  Enactus  India  and  puts  up  stalls  in  various  events  organised  by
               college societies and corporate offices. It’s project Misbah, aided rescued sex workers by teaching
               them  candle  making  through  online  training  sessions,  making  them  financially  independent.
               Enactus Maitreyi took many initiatives in the session 2020-2021, like Online Mental Wellness
               Sessions, Social Media Awareness on Grave Issues, launch of a new Spotify range of candles for
               every mood, to name a few. Enactus Maitreyi believes in making a change irrespective of the
               harsh times.

               SPORTS
               The sports students of Maitreyi College have brought laurels to the college by winning in various
               sports events at the University and National level. Many of the players have represented the
               country too in their respective fields. Facilities are available for individual and team games such
               as Athletics, Basketball, Boxing, Cricket, Football, Hockey, Judo, Netball, Powerlifting, Softball,
               Taekwondo, Volleyball, Weightlifting, and Yoga. The College established a sports centre, Pragati:
               Center for netball & facility dedicated to imparting physical ability and techniques for playing
               netball in India. The centre organized 33rd Junior National Netball camp for women from 10-22
               February 2021 at Maitreyi College, sports Ground, where 20 girls attended the camp. There is
               also a Center for sports for persons with intellectual disabilities, Special Olympic Bharat. The
               sports department organised an online Yoga Session for sports students from 7 am to 8 am every
               Friday and Saturday from September 2020 to March 2021.


                                 Note: All students are required to join at least one of
                                 these co-curricular activities, viz. NCC, NSS and Sports


                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 26]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               COLLEGE MAGAZINE
               The College releases an annual magazine wherein the literary and creative talent of the students
               is given an adequate expression through their contribution to the magazine.

               STUDENTS' UNION
               Maitreyi College is proud of its active, vibrant, well-balanced and responsible Students' Union. It
               comprises of elected representatives of the student body who undertake the task of organizing
               co-curricular activities for various inter- and intra-College competitions. They are guided by a
               group of faculty advisors who help to coordinate their activities. Students are encouraged to join
               music, dance, dramatics, debate and fine arts societies. 'RHAPSODY', the Annual inter-College
               Cultural festival, organized by the Students' Union every year in winter is one of the most eagerly
               awaited events of the College.

               STUDENTS' SOCIETIES

               ABHIVYAKTI- Theatre Society
               Abhivyakti is an active group for theatre enthusiasts. The society works religiously for social
               awareness and self-upliftment. In the academic session 2020-21, Abhivyakti created an offline
               Stage play production ‘---------- ki matra galat hai’ amidst pandemic with the spirit to keep the
               value of art alive. It also created the online ‘MOVIE SCREENING’ event, where the artistic picture
               ‘Mera Ram Kho Gaya’ was screened. The team participated in a number of online events and
               secured multiple prizes in many reputed colleges and universities.

               APOLLONIA- Western Music Society
               Apollonia is the newest society established to embark on the journey to unite the world with the
               means of music. The society intends to include and explore as many languages and genres of
               music. The team organized an online Canzonet, solo singing competition through Google meet
               during Rhapsody’21. It organized an online AcaHella, ACAPELLA competition.  Apollonia also
               participated  in  a  number  of  other  online  competitions  organized  by  various  different
               colleges/universities.

               ARTISTO- Fine Arts Society
               Artisto, in its four years of existence, has already established itself as a distinguished society
               among the fine arts societies of University of Delhi. The society has been successful in bringing
               together a diverse group of creative minds together. Artisto not only emphasizes on inculcating
               creative  elements  in  the  personality  of  its  members  and  the  community  but  pays  diligent
               attention to making the community learn how to use the skills in real world. To further this
               experience, Artisto held several online workshops (like watercolours, coffee painting, and pen
               rendering) and competitions throughout the year.

               GALORE- Fashion Society
               The fashion society of Maitreyi College, Galore symbolizing grace, confidence, attitude & elegance
               has been active for more than a decade. It is built by fashion lovers who set aside the norms of
               the  society  &  break  the  stereotypes  by  their  sterling  performances  and  scintillating  themes.
               Galore participated in the annual fest of Lady Irwin College and bagged first position in the
               competition. Two particiapnats of the team also received the titles of Best Female Model and Best
               Attitude on Stage in the annual fest of Sri Aurobindo College. Overall, Galore has been able to
               maintain its position in the fashion circuit despite the challenging times.

                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 27]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               NRITYAKRITI- Indian Dance Society
               Nrityakriti, the Indian dance society, is now travelling in its 9  year of journey successfully
                                                                              th
               with the support of our conveners, the college management and the teachers. It has made its
               remarkable  mark  among  the  classical  and  folk  dance  circuit  of  Delhi  University  by
               showcasing the talent of the team members. It has been adjudged as “The Best and Top Folk
               Dance  Society”  by  DU  beat  in  the  past  years.  Under  the  series  of  online  competitions
               organized  during  Rhapsody’21,  Nrityakriti  curated  two  online  dance  competitions:
               MALANG-  Solo/  Duet  Folk  Dance  Competition  and  PRATYANG-  Solo  Classical  Dance
               Competition.

               PRAKRITI- Eco Club
               Prakriti, the eco club of Maitreyi College, aims at sensitizing people towards earth, nature,
               and life. It remains active throughout the academic session and organizes several webinars
               and online competitions that generate awareness on important environmental issues among
               the students and teachers.

               RIYAAZ- Indian Music Society
               Riyaaz, is a group of young music enthusiasts who delve into finding peace and tranquillity
               by reaching out to every possible genre of Indian music. Raagas, Ghazals, Sufi and Bollywood
               music are the fortes of the society. It not only focuses on winning accolades, but also bringing
               harmony to one's life and positivity to others through its music. Over the span of a few years,
               Riyaaz is seen to have risen to become a well-coordinated and dedicated band of talented
               girls. Riyaaz organizes its annual fest ‘SWAROTSAV’, wherein students participate from all
               over India. ‘SWAROTSAV’ consists of different components: AAROHI (Indian classical/ Light
               solo competition) and SWARAGINI (Indian Instrumental Competition).

               TRENCHANT- English Debating Society
               Trenchant, the english debating society, is best known for its participation in competitions
               such as parliamentary debate, conventional debate, creative writing, paper presentation,
               model united nations, etc. on an inter-College and inter-University level. It has three wings:
               the  Parliamentary  Debate  Wing  (PD),  the  Model  United  Nations  Wing  (MUN)  and  the
               Creative Writing Wing (CW). Since the primary mode of communication has shifted online,
               the  members  have  been  able  to  access  a  much  greater  variety  of  competitions,  both
               nationally and internationally. The members have shown their utmost dedication towards
               society through regularly attending sessions, accommodating with the uncertainties caused
               by the pandemic, or bagging numerous laurels.

               VAACHIK- Hindi Debating Society
               The  society  aims  to  train  students  to  express  their  independent,  logical  and  analytical
               opinions through the Hindi language on the subject and improve their communication skills
               based on the facts and figures. This society, having 17 students, has set up new horizons of
               success in the academic year 2020-2021 by winning 11 first, 8 second and 9 third prize in
               State as well as National debate, poem, slogan and essay writing competitions. The society,
               along  with  Students’  Union  of  the  College,  organized  for  the  first  time  an  online  debate
               competition,  titled  ‘Aatm  Nirbhar  Bharat  Vartmaan  Samay  Ke  Avashyakta  Hai’  on  the



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 28]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               occasion of Independence Day. The students of the society won many first and second prizes
               in online debate events organized by various colleges of Delhi University.

               VISTA- Photography Society
               VISTA is a bundle of people who thrive to capture moments with a camera always in their
               hands. It’s a close-knit family that provides its members’ freedom to explore and nourish
               their skills while helping them carve a niche for themselves. The society has been the birthing
               ground of the best photographers of Maitreyi College each year. The society has been very
               active throughout the session and the team organized numerous online photography events,
               competitions, workshops and photowalks.

               ZEAL- Western Dance Society
               Zeal, the western dance society of the Maitreyi College is defined by its bounteous energy,
               unrelenting dedication, creativity and passion for dance. Apart from the colleges of Delhi
               University, Zeal has done exceptionally well in various outstation fests by securing many
               prizes. The society organized an online dance competition ‘Match the Beat’, which received
               participation from the universities all over India.

                FACILITIES

               LIBRARY AND READING ROOM
               The Library block is located in a spacious two-storied building. The ground floor houses the
               book stacks, the periodical section and the circulation counter. The first floor has a separate
               reference  section  and  reading  room  facility  for  students  and  staff.  The  library  has  an
               extensive collection, which includes print and non-print material as well as e-resources like
               CDs, DVDs, e-journals, e-books. The library has a corpus of more than 99,307 print books and
               678 CDs. It subscribes to 57 Journals, including popular magazines, and a collection of 23
               newspapers.  The  library  subscribes  N-LIST  Consortium, which  covers  6,000+  ejournals,
               1,64,300+  ebooks  under  N-LIST  and  6,00,000  ebooks  through  NDL.  The  College  Library
               continues  to  be  the  member  of  DELNET  (Developing  Library  Network),  which  specially
               caters our need through Inter Library Loan. It consists of a huge number of e-resources like
               e-journals, e-books, online dictionaries, thesis and dissertations etc. Library has created its
               own Institutional repository using DSPACE software, which is accessible in the library only.
               Library users can access the previous and current year syllabus through Maitreyi College
               Library Repository and the college website.

               INTERNET FACILITY AND ELECTRONIC INFORMATION RESOURCE CENTRE
               The e-library and resource centre in the library with computers (provided by the University
               of Delhi) offers the students access to internet and printout facility free of cost. The electronic
               resources subscribed by University of Delhi and UGC-infonet resources are accessible here.
               The College library also subscribes to e-books/ journals/ Databases through N-LIST. Any
               user can access these resources at the College or at their own place through internet. The
               College has setup Wi-Fi LAN connectivity with 19 APs. Video conferencing equipments are
               also available in the College to conduct virtual classes.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 29]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               LABORATORIES
               The College has 15 very well equipped laboratories for practical in subjects like Computer
               Science, Chemistry, Botany, Zoology and Physics. A new Science Block will be functional in
               the upcoming session.

               BOOKSTORE
               The College bookstore offers a wide selection of texts and other books. Various stationery
               items and mementos are also available.

               ENABLING UNIT AND EQUAL OPPORTUNITY CELL
               The Enabling Unit provides internet, scanning (in bi-lingual mode) and printing facility to all
               its members and students. It organized a number of National Webinars during the academic
               session. Equal Opportunity Cell has renewed Writer and Reader’s Bank which was developed
               as per the new examination policy of Delhi University for Persons with Disabilities. This bank
               always  helps  the  students  as  well  as  faculty  members  belonging  to  the  PwD  category
               whenever required. Enabling Unit, in collaboration with the School of Indic Studies, Institute
               of  Advanced  Science  organized  a  Three  Months  Certificate  Course  of  Skill  Development
               (International  Level)  on  ‘Applications  of  Digital  Tools  in  Teaching  and  Learning  Indian
               Languages’. It also conducted India’s Two Week Faculty Development Program/ Refresher
               Course on ‘Emerging Accessible Technologies for Teachers in Higher Education’.

               PLACEMENT CELL
               The  placement  cell  acts  as  a  liaison  between  the  corporate  world  and  the  prospective
               students.  It  helps  to  identify  the  potential  capabilities  of  the  students  and  guide  them
               towards the right career path. It focuses on providing the students with ample opportunities
               be it jobs or internships to choose from in the fields of arts, sciences and commerce. The
               placement  cell  conducts  seminars,  workshops  and  career  counseling  sessions  for  skill
               enhancement with a  prime  focus on  providing career guidance. In the academic session
               2020-21, in the middle of a pandemic, where people were losing their jobs, the cell opened a
               door  of  opportunities  for  the  students  of  the  college  as  well  as  students  from  different
               colleges registered in Delhi during Envision 3.0, the Annual Job and Internship Fair. The cell
               has brought in 65 companies offering jobs to over 75 students out of 270 registrants with
               the average salary offered being ₹4.8 lakh. The recruiters were companies like DE Shaw
               Group, MedicFibres, Bajaj Capital, Amazon, and many more.

               ACHIEVEMENT CELL
               The  Achievement  Cell  works  to  harness  the  power  of  Maitreyians  as  a  community  by
               bringing to the forefront their achievements and training them in diverse areas. Its goal is to
               build a strong legacy for the institution. In this regard, over 80+ high achieving students have
               been identified since its inception in August 2018. The team conducts group discussions on
               issues of international importance, hosts competitions, projects, and collaborates with other
               societies and cells in order to create a  spirit  of excellence among students  and  to  make
               Maitreyi College a promising path to success.





                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 30]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               MERAKI- The Entrepreneurship Cell
               Meraki,  the  entrepreneurship  cell  was  founded  in  the  year  2019,  with  the  objective  to
               provide  a  learning  platform  to  the  budding  women  entrepreneurs  of  Maitreyi  College.
               Throughout  the  session,  Meraki  organized  a  series  of  Webinars,  Campaigns,  Start-ups,
               Projects, Competitions and 'The Annual E-Summit Entrescope’21. It launched a total of 4
               start-ups  with  different  objectives.  A  number  of  startups,  in  collaboration  with  other
               students’ societies and committees are ongoing; like, ECOHANDY, an initiative to make and
               sell paper-based pens; STAY MENTOR, a startup that aims at providing housing solutions to
               outstation students of Maitreyi College.

               HEALTH AND HYGIENE COMMITTEE
               Health  &  hygiene  committee  of  the  college  is  an  active  committee  to  generate  health
               awareness amongst students, teaching and non-teaching staff. During the academic session
               2020-21, it organized several webinars like ‘Immunity through Nutrition’, ‘Online Teaching-
               Learning and Eye Care’, ‘Orthopaedic Care and Precautions’,  and ‘Breast Cancer: Prevention
               and Early Detection’.

               INTERNAL COMPLAINTS COMMITTEE
               The internal complaints cell against sexual harassment has its goal to spread awareness,
               extend support, and attempt to come up with solutions. It organized various online inter-
               college competitions in its fest called ‘Adamya’ to create awareness on gender related issues.
               It published two issues of its bilingual e-magazine, Samvedna, during the academic session
               2020-21, and were uploaded on the college website.

               GARDEN
               The College is proud of its well-maintained, beautiful lush green lawns, trees, plants, rock
               garden, rose garden and gerbal garden. To create and nurture a natural, peaceful fascinating
               ambience with the natural world is the heart of the college garden’s mission. There is also a
               Garden Club ‘Pristine’ in the college, with the aim to connect students with nature and initiate
               new garden features and environment friendly activities to inspire and strengthen college’s
               commitment to the environment. The students of the club have successfully embraced the
               changes needed to respond to the challenges of climate change by means of reusing the waste
               plastic bottles as planters, waste bins and sitting stools.
               The dedicated gardeners are essential to achieving our mission and the number of awards
               the college receives at the Delhi University flower show held annually can see their hard
               work. This year also the College won many laurels like, best herbal garden in the University-
               Meenakshi Gopinath Cup, best garden in the University- Department of Persian Cup, second
               prizes in Lawn, ‘Clean and Green Campus’, and third prize in Rose Garden. To make the best
               use of resources, an initiative to provide faculty and staff with fruits such as Amla growing
               in the college garden has been started and will soon be extended by providing vegetables
               and medicinal plants grown organically on the campus on a need basis.

               COLLEGE CANTEEN
               The College canteen serves as a pleasant eating and meeting place for students.



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 31]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               RO PURIFIED DRINKING WATER
               As part of infrastructure development an RO System along with water dispensers has been
               installed to cater to the entire College building with a capacity of 1000 liters per hour.

               SURVEILLANCE SYSTEM
               CCTV network of 16 cameras has been installed for enhanced security of the College and a
               public address  system has been put in place  for faster intra-College communication  and
               announcements.

               MEDICAL ROOM
               The College medical room provides basic medicines and has first-aid facilities if the need
               arises. A staff nurse is present in the medical room every day and a doctor visits the College
               on appointed days.

               LEGAL AID CELL
               The College is associated with the Delhi Legal Services Authority, which works towards the
               constitutional  obligation  of  the  state  to  ensure  legal  aid  and  guidance  for  the  College
               community.

               ALUMNI ASSOCIATION (SANNIDHYA)
               Our old students' association organizes a get together once a year in the College premises to
               honour distinguished alumni. This year, it organized e-Sannidhya 2021, the Annual Alumni
               Meet,  to  bring  together  alumni,  faculty  and  students,  albeit  virtually  and  celebrate  their
               mutual association with the Maitreyi kutumb.
               Maitreyi takes great pride in the achievements and contributions of all its alumni.
                   Squadron leader Veena Saharan is the only woman pilot who has qualified as Captain to
                    fly  IL-76,  transport  aircraft,  largest  (190,000  kg)  flying  machine  in  the  inventory  of
                    Indian Air Force.
                   Ms. Jyoti Challi is Founder, President and CEO of Banyan Solutions. She won the Women
                    of Distinction, 2016 Award by New York magazine. She combined her technology skills
                    with  her  passion  for  healthcare  and  formed  'Banyan  Solutions,  Inc.'  a  medical
                    transcription and medical billing company.
                   Dr. Prem Mohini (Ph.D. and MS in Biochemistry, and a specialized certificate in Clinical
                    Trials and Administration) is a pre-clinical hands-on researcher, project leader, and a
                    presenter in academic sector.
                   Dr.  R.  Mahalaxmi  (Ph.D  in  Carnatic  Music,  DU)  is  a  professional  singer  and  is  also
                    recipient of the 'Asian Peace Award'. She was awarded the Title 'Miss Nightingale' by the
                    Delhi Tamil Education Association (DTEA) in the year 1998 for excellence in Music.
                   Ms. Ranjani Rao is academic advisor with the Department of Computer Science at Purdue
                    University.
                   Ms.  Aastha  Gandhi  is  currently  a  part  of  the  research  project:  'Cultures  of  the  Left'
                    between Jawaharlal Nehru University and University of Warwick, UK. She is a regular
                    member of World Dance Alliance.
                   Ms. Pooja Shali is a principal correspondent with the English News Channel-Times Now.




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 32]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                   Ms. Vijeta Sharma has been an assistant director for several Bollywood films. She has a
                    Hollywood documentary based on Swarovski to her credit. She is also a professional
                    mountaineer and has climbed 6 and 7 thousander peaks. She also worked as an official
                    reporter for the Government of Uttarakhand.
                   Ms. Manya Narang is a professional singer and one among the top 8 finalists in Indian
                    Idol 2017. She has won many regional and state level awards.
                   Ms. Kritika Sobti is a successful model who has appeared for several companies like
                    Oriflame, Nikon, Fabindia, Sabhyata, Bonsoir, Vogue, Radio Nasha 107.2 FM and Radio
                    Fever 104 FM etc. Recently she has also featured in various chartbusters.
                   Dr Latika Nath Rana one of India's foremost experts on tigers, is a Wildlife Biologist with
                    a Ph.D. from Oxford. The National Geographic documented her life and work and tagged
                    her the 'India's Tiger Princess'. Currently she continues to live and work in the field,
                    where each day is a fight to keep the impending threat of tiger extinction at bay, despite
                    a major lack of funds.
                   Major Poonam Sangwan currently posted in Akhnoor, is a recipient of the prestigious
                    Vishisht Sewa medal and Chief of Army Staff commendation card for exemplary and
                    distinguished services. She has scaled numerous heights, literally and figuratively. She
                    was a part of the Indian Army Everest expedition in 2012, a testimony to her tremendous
                    potential and perseverance.
                   Dr.  Livleen  Shukla  Principal  Scientist  at  Indian  Agricultural  Research  Institute  has
                    published widely in both English and Hindi-a feat worth emulating, with more than 50
                    publications  to  her  credit.  She  also  contributes  to  the  society  at  large  through  her
                    research projects.
                   Dr. Ipsita Roy an Associate Professor at National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education
                    and Research (NIPER), a recipient of the prestigious, Alexander von Humboldt Research
                    Fellowship,  Germany;  has  mentored  many  Ph.D.  students  and  has  a  hundred
                    publications of International repute to her credit.
                   Ms. Soumitra Dev Burman a professional singer, she was honoured with the Best Singer
                    Award by the Sangam Kala Group, New Delhi and Best Singer Award, Pratishruthi in
                    Assam for three consecutive years. A Human Resource Development (HRD) Scholarship
                    holder, Ministry of Tourism, she has worked as an All India Radio Artist and dubbed for
                    films and various albums.
                   Dr. Neera Sen Sarkar currently associated with Kalyani University, Kolkata, West Bengal,
                    has supervised several Ph.D., authored various books and published her research in
                    journals of National and International repute. For her astounding contribution to her
                    field  she  was  awarded  the  Fast  Track  Young  Scientist  Award  from  Science  and
                    Engineering Research Board, New Delhi.
                   Ms. Sonal Rihani a star performer and blend of valour and glamour, Miss India Kolkata
                    2014, a finalist for Miss India 2014 and cover girl for Femina West Magazine, has done
                    numerous shows such as India Couture Week 2017 and Femina Style Fashion Fiesta
                    Season 4 and 5.
                   Major Nupur Gupta is a retired army officer with 25 years of experience in teaching,
                    training and leadership development.

               Note: Every student in final year (VI semester) has to get alumni card made.

                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 33]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                DEPARTMENTS AND FACULTY

       BOTANY DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Alka B. Vadakan, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                Dr. Sandeepa Singh, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.
       Dr. Adesh Rani, M.Sc., Ph.D.                              Dr. Pooja Baweja, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.
       Ms. Divya Singh, M.Sc., M.Phil.                           Dr. P. Kavita, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.
       Dr. Atika Chandra, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                  Dr. Anamika Singh, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Rama Sisodia, M.Sc., Ph.D. (Incharge)

       CHEMISTRY DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Pinkey Bajaj Gandhi, M.Sc., Ph.D.                     Dr. Rajni Johar Chhatwal, M.Sc., Ph.D. (Incharge)
       Dr. Sandhya Gupta, M.Sc., Ph.D.                           Dr. Pratibha Chaudhary, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Padma Saxena, M.Sc., Ph.D.                            Dr. Hema Bhandari, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Gita Batra Narula, M.Sc., Ph.D.                       Dr. Ritu Gaba, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Manju Mehta, M.Sc., Ph.D.                             Dr. Lata Vodwal, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Haritma Chopra, M.Sc., Ph.D. (Offg. Principal)        Dr. Ankita Chaudhary, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Ramesh Kumari, M.Sc., Ph.D.                           Mr. Kamal Sharma, M.Sc., M.Phil.

       COMMERCE DEPARTMENT
       Ms. Nirmala Chauhan, M.Com.                               Mr. Ginmunlal Khongsai, M.Com.
       Dr. Prachi Bagla, M.Com, M.Phil., Ph.D.(Bursar)           Ms. Latika Poswal Tanwar, M.Com.
       Dr. Sonal Babbar, M.Com., M. Phil., Ph.D. (Incharge)  Ms. Shweta Tripathi, M.Com, M.Phil.
       Ms. Shaifali, M.Com, PGDOM                                Dr. Vidisha Garg, M.Com., Ph.D.
       Ms. Jyotsna, L.L.B., M.Com.                               Ms. Neha, M.Com., M. Phil.

       COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Manju Bhardwaj, MCA, Ph.D.                                   Dr. Shikha Badhani, MCA, Ph.D.
       Dr. Veena Ghuriani, MCA, Ph.D. (Incharge)                 Dr. Jyotsna Talreja Wassan, M.Sc., Ph. D.

       ECONOMICS DEPARTMENT
       Ms. Rachna Jain, M.A., M.Phil.                            Ms. Antima Jain, M.A.
       Ms. Aruna Saluja, M.A., M.Phil.                           Ms. Artika Vats, M.A.
       Ms. Nidhi Chand, M.A., M.Phil.                            Ms. Nupur Kataria, M.A., M.Phil.
       Dr. Saroj Rani, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.                      Ms. N. Shradha Varma, M.A. (Incharge)
       Dr. Priti  Mendiratta Arora, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.

       ENGLISH DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Smriti Singh, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.                    Ms. Manisha Saluja, M.A., M.Phil.
       Ms. M. Tianla, M.A., M.Phil. (Incharge)                   Dr. Monica Chhabra, M.A., Ph.D.
       Ms. Rachna Sirohi, M.A., M.Phil.

       HINDI/ PUNJABI DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Surinder Kaur Malhotra, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D. (Incharge)

                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 34]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




       HISTORY DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Ranjana Bhattacharya, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.            Dr. Ritu C. Kumar, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.
                                                                 (Incharge)

       LIBRARY
       Dr. Pardeep Rai, M.A., M.L.I.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.
       (Librarian)

       MATHEMATICS DEPARTMENT
       Ms. Rajni Gupta, M.A., M.Phil.                            Ms. Geetan Manchanda, M.Sc., M.Phil.
                                                                 (Incharge)

       PHYSICAL EDUCATION DEPARTMENT
       Ms. Shipra Verma, M.P.Ed., M.Phil. (Incharge)

       PHYSICS DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Veena Mishra, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                   Dr. Shalini Lumb Talwar, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Poonam Juneja, M.Sc., Ph.D.                           Ms. Polly Biswas, M.Sc.
       Dr. Ritu Dhingra, M.Sc., Ph.D. (Incharge)                 Dr. Swapna Ray Jain, M.Sc., Ph.D.

       POLITICAL SCIENCE DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Kiran Pandey, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D. (Incharge)         Dr. Mithila Bagai, M.A., Ph.D.
       Mr. Yogesh Chaurasia, M.A.

       SANSKRIT DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Pramod Kumar Singh, M.A., M.Phil, Ph.D.               Dr. Sushil Kumari, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.
                                                                 (Incharge)

       SOCIOLOGY DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Anurita Jalan, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.                   Dr. Gopi Devdutt Tripathy, M.A., M.Phil., Ph.D.
                                                                 (Incharge)

       ZOOLOGY DEPARTMENT
       Dr. Versha Goel, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                    Dr. Rakhi Gupta, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D. (Incharge)
       Dr. Jyoti Singh, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                    Dr. Anshu Arora Anand, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Renu Gupta, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                           Dr. Archana Aggarwal, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.
       Dr. Brototi Roy, M.Sc., M.Phil., Ph.D.                    Dr. Shilpa Bharti, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Meena Yadav, M.Sc., Ph.D.                             Dr. Jaspreet Kaur, M.Sc., Ph.D.
       Dr. Luni, M.Sc., Ph.D.






                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 35]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




                         Grievance Committee for Redressal of Grievances (General Queries)
                                     Related to Undergraduate Admission 2021-22
                    Dr. Artika Vats                9711833874                   avats@maitreyi.du.ac.in
                    Dr. Pardeep Rai                9311331437
                    Mr. Satya Dev Singh            9311331436
                    Mr. Praveen Kumar              9717425071

                              Special Categories Admission Enabling Committee 2021-22
                    Dr. Smriti Singh            English Department                          8130789917
                    Dr. Pramod Kumar Singh   Sanskrit Department                            9717189242
                    Mr. Yogesh Chaurasia        Political Science Department                9868485583
                    Ms. Kamlesh Bhalla          Offg. Section Officer (Admn.)               9871073949

                             Help Desk Committee for Undergraduate Admission 2021-22
                                                (Subject Specific Queries)
                       Dr. Pardeep Rai                    Convener                            9899359373
                       Dr. Surinder Kaur Malhotra           B. A. (P)                         9999756955
                    Dr. Harmeet Kaur                    B. A. (P)                           9650472729
                    Dr. Pushpa Gupta                    B. A. (P)                           9873712335
                       Dr. Sneh Lata                       B. A. (P)
                       Ms. Kanchan Kumari                  B. A. (P)                           8285352722
                       Dr. Dharmendra Kumar                B. A. (P)                           9560828509
                       Dr. Rama Sisodia                      Botany Department                 9958533854
                    Dr. Pratibha Chaudhary              Chemistry Department                9650516662
                    Dr. Sonal Babbar                    Commerce Department                 9910303280
                    Dr. Vidisha Garg                    Commerce Department                 9818266671
                       Dr. N Shraddha Varma                Economics Department                9873452637
                    Dr. Smriti Singh                    English Department                  8130789917
                    Dr. Anita Devi                      Hindi Department                    9899840037
                    Dr. Ranjana Bhattacharya            History Department                  9654217107
                       Dr. Sandeepa Singh                  Life Sciences                       9212064428
                       Dr Eapsa Berry                      Life Sciences                       9811686091
                    Ms. Geetan Manchanda                      Mathematics Department        9911554067
                       Dr. Rajni Johar Chhatwal                     Physical Sciences                  9643676309
                    Dr. Ritu Dhingra                    Physics Department                  9868538992
                    Dr. Kiran Pandey                    Political Science Department        9868732554
                    Dr. Kanika Gupta                    Political Science Department        9811507458
                    Dr. Sushil Kumari                         Sanskrit Department           9968730615
                    Dr. Anurita Jalan                   Sociology Department                9810179561
                    Dr. Rakhi Gupta                     Zoology Department                  9910104552
                    Dr. A Vineetha                                  Zoology Department       8800687212
                    Dr. Ritu Gaba                       ECA                                 9811899839
                    Ms. Shipra Verma                    Sports/ Physical Education          7042577899




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 36]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE




               OPTIONAL SUBJECTS/ PAPERS



                OPTIONS FOR DISCIPLINE COURSES IN B.A. (PROGRAMME)
                Students may opt for any one combination of discipline courses, which will continue till third
                year.
                S. No.        DSC-1A                                   DSC-IB
                1             Political Science                        History
                2             Political Science                        Sociology
                3             Political Science                        Hindi Discipline
                4             Political Science                        Sanskrit
                5             Political Science                        Punjabi Discipline
                6             History                                  Hindi Discipline
                7             History                                  Punjabi Discipline
                8             History                                  Sanskrit
                9             Sociology                                English Discipline
                10            Economics                                English Discipline
                11            Economics                                Mathematics
                12            Economics                                Computer Applications
                13            Computer Applications                    Mathematics


                ABILITY ENHANCEMENT COMPULSORY COURSE OPTIONS
                                           B.A.          B.Com.        B.Com.        B.Sc.        B.Sc.
                SEMESTER     B.A. (PROG.)
                                           (HONOURS)     (PROG.)       (HONOURS)     (PROG.)      (HONOURS)
                             English/      English/      EVS           EVS           EVS          EVS
                I            MIL           MIL

                             EVS           EVS           English/      English/      English/     English/
                II
                                                         MIL           MIL           MIL          MIL
               (MIL: Hindi/ Punjabi/ Sanskrit)


               THE COLLEGE SHALL BE OFFERING THE FOLLOWING SUBJECTS/ PAPERS AS GENERIC
               ELECTIVE/ DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE:

                GENERIC ELECTIVE PAPER FOR B.Com. (PROGRAMME)


                V Semester                                      VI Semester

                Principles of Microeconomics                    Principles of Macroeconomics






                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 37]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





                GENERIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.A. (HONOURS)/ B.Com. (HONOURS)
                SUBJECT           I Semester          II Semester         III Semester      IV Semester
                                                      Finance for Non-                      Insurance and
                                  Basics of                               Investing in
                COMMERCE                              finance                               Risk
                                  Accounting                              Stock Markets
                                                      Executives                            Management
                                                      Database                              Multimedia
                COMPUTER          Programming         Management          Computer          Systems and
                SCIENCE           using Python                            Networks
                                                      System                                Applications

                                  Introductory        Introductory        Indian
                ECONOMICS                                                                   Public Finance
                                  Microeconomics      Macroeconomics  Economy-I

                                                      Readings on
                                  Academic            Indian              Media and         Language,
                ENGLISH           Writing and         Diversities and     Communica-        Literature and
                                  Composition         Literary            tion Skills       Culture
                                                      Movements

                                                                                                     ै
                                                                                              िं
                                          े
                                    िं
                                                                   िं
                                  ह दी हिनमा और       पटकथा और िवाद                         ह दी का वशहवक
                HINDI                                                     भाषा और िमाज
                                                        े
                                  उिका अध्ययन         लखन                                   पररदृश्य
                                  Delhi through       Delhi through
                                  the Ages: The       the Ages II: From  The Making of
                HISTORY           Making of its       Colonial to         Contemporary      Inequality and
                                  Early Modern        Contemporary        India             Differences
                                  History             Times
                                                                          Differential      Numerical
                MATHEMATICS  Calculus                 Linear Algebra
                                                                          Equations         Methods
                                                                                            Fitness and
                PHYSICAL          Yoga and Stress     Obesity             Aerobics          Exercise
                EDUCATION         Management          Management          Training
                                                                                            Management
                                                      Gandhi and the                        United Nations
                POLITICAL         Nationalism in      Contemporary        Understanding     and Global
                SCIENCE           India                                   Ambedkar
                                                      World                                 Conflicts

                                                                                            Basic Principles
                                                                                            of Indian
                                                      Nationalism and     Ancient Indian
                SANSKRIT          Basic Sanskrit                                            Medicine
                                                      Indian Literature  Polity
                                                                                            System
                                                                                            (Ayurveda)

                                  Indian Society:
                SOCIOLOGY         Images and          Sociology of        Rethinking        Gender and
                                                                                            Violence
                                                      Education
                                                                          Development
                                  Realities


                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 38]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





                GENERIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.Sc. (HONOURS)


                SUBJECT             I Semester         II Semester        III Semester      IV Semester


                                    Biodiversity                          Plant
                                    (Microbes, Algae,  Plant  Ecology
                BOTANY                                                    Physiology and
                                    Fungi         and  and Taxonomy       Metabolism
                                    Archegoniatae)


                                                       s- and p-block
                                    Atomic Structure  Elements
                CHEMISTRY           and     Chemical  States of Matter
                                    Bonding            Molecules      of
                                                       Life
                                                                          Differential      Numerical
                MATHEMATICS         Calculus           Linear Algebra
                                                                          Equations         Methods
                                    Electricity   and                     Waves       and  Thermal
                PHYSICS                                Mechanics
                                    Magnetism                             Optics            Physics

                                                       Human              Food  Nutrition
                ZOOLOGY             Animal Diversity
                                                       Physiology         and Health




                GENERIC ELECTIVE AND SKILL ENHANCEMENT SUBJECTS FOR B.A. (PROGRAMME)

                                  III and IV Semester                   V and VI Semester
                                                                        Commerce
                                                                        Computer Science
                                                                        Economics
                GE                                                      History
                                                                        Hindi
                                                                        Punjabi
                                                                        Sociology
                                  Computer Science                      Economics
                                  Economics                             English

                SEC                                                     Punjabi
                                  Hindi/ Punjabi                        Political Science

                                  History                               Sociology
                One subject is to be chosen in each semester




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 39]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





                DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.A. (HONOURS)
                               V Semester                              VI Semester
                SUBJECT
                               DSE I                DSE II             DSE I               DSE II
                                                                       I-A Political       II-A Law and
                               I-A Political        II-A Public        Economy II          Economics
                               Economy I            Economics
                ECONOMICS                                              I-B Money and       II-B
                               I-B International    II-B Financial     Financial           Environmental
                               Economics            Economics
                                                                       Markets             Economics
                               I-A Modern           II-A Science
                               Indian Writing in    Fiction and        I-A Literature      II-A Partition
                               English
                ENGLISH        Translation          Detective          and Cinema          Literature
                                                                       I-B Literary
                                                    Literature
                                                                                           II-B World
                               I-B Literature of    II-B Literary      Theory              Literature
                               the Indian           Criticism
                               Diaspora
                                                          िं
                                     िं
                               I-A ह दी की          II-A ह दी  भाषा
                               मौखखक और लोक         का व्यव ाररक       I-A लोकनाट्य        II-A अवधारणात्मक
                                       िं
                HINDI          िाह त्य परपरा        व्याकरण            I-B ह दी की भाहषक    िाह खत्यक पद
                                                                             िं
                               I-B भारतीय एव  िं    II-B कोष हवज्ञान:   हवहवधताए  िं       II-B ह दी रगमच
                                                                                                    िं
                                                                                                 िं
                                                                                                       िं
                                         िं
                                      िं
                               पाश्चात्य रगमच       शब्दकोष और
                                   िं
                               हिद्ात               हवश्वकोश
                               I-A History of       II-A History of    I-A History of      II-A History of
                               USA:                 Modern China       USA:                Modern Japan
                               Independence to      (1840-1960)        Reconstruction      and Korea
                               Civil War                               to New Age          (1868- 1950s)
                HISTORY                             II-B History of
                               I-B History of       Southeast Asia     Politics            II-B History of
                               USSR: From           upto the 16        I-B History of      Southeast Asia:
                                                               th
                               Revolution to        Century            USSR: The Soviet  17  to 20
                                                                                                     th
                                                                                              th
                               World War II                            Experience          Century
                                                    Development
                                                    Process and                            India's Foreign
                               Colonialism and                         Citizenship in a
                POLITICAL                           Social                                 Policy in a
                SCIENCE        Nationalism in       Movements in       Globalizing         Globalizing
                               India                                   World
                                                    Contemporary                           World
                                                    India
                               Theatre and          Sanskrit           Fundamentals of  Art of Balanced
                SANSKRIT
                               Dramaturgy           Linguistics        Ayurveda            Living


                               Urban Sociology                                            Visual Cultures
                               Sociology of Work                                         Indian Sociological Traditions
                SOCIOLOGY
                               Environmental Sociology                           Sociology of Health and Medicine
                               Agrarian Sociology                                        Reading Ethnographies



                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 40]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





                 DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.Com. (PROGRAMME)
                V Semester                                         VI Semester

                Fundamentals of Financial Management               Fundamentals of Investment



                DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.A. (PROGRAMME)
                SUBJECT                 V Semester                         VI Semester

                                                                           Information Security and Cyber
                COMPUTER SCIENCE  Programming with Python
                                                                           Laws

                                        Economic  Development  and  Economic  Development  and
                ECONOMICS
                                        Policy in India I                  Policy in India II
                ENGLISH                 Detective Literature               World Literature
                                          िं
                HINDI                   ह दी भाषा का व्यवा ररक व्याकरण     कोष हवज्ञान शब्दकोष और हवश्वकोश
                                        Europe from Middle Ages to the
                HISTORY                                                    History of Europe (1500-1848)
                                        Renaissance (7  to 16  Century)
                                                              th
                                                       th
                MATHEMATICS             Statistics                         Numerical Methods

                                        Administration     and     Public
                POLITICAL SCIENCE                                          Understanding Globalization
                                        Policy: Concepts and Theories
                                        History  of  Punjabi  Literature
                PUNJABI                 (from beginning period to 1900     History  of  Punjabi  Literature
                                                                           (from 1900 AD to present)
                                        AD)
                                        Nationalism       in     Sanskrit  Indian       Perspectives       in
                SANSKRIT
                                        Literature                         Personality Development

                SOCIOLOGY               Marriage, Family and Kinship       Social Stratification


                DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.Com. (HONOURS)

                V Semester                                     VI Semester
                DSE I                   DSE II                 DSE I                   DSE II
                                        II-A Advertising                               II-A International
                I-A Management          and Personal           I-A Fundamentals of     Business
                Accounting              Selling                Investment              II-B Industrial
                I-B Entrepreneurship    II-B Business          I-B Consumer Affairs    Relations and Labour
                Development                                    and Customer Care
                                        Statistics                                     Laws




                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 41]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





                DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.Sc. (PROGRAMME)
                                     V Semester                          VI Semester
                SUBJECT
                                     DSE I-A         DSE I-B             DSE II-A          DSE II-B

                                     Cell and                            Economic          Analytical
                LIFE SCIENCES        Molecular       Bioinformatics      Botany and        Techniques in
                (BOTANY)
                                     Biology                             Biotechnology     Plant Sciences


                                                                         States of Matter and Chemical
                                     Atomic Structure and Chemical       Equilibrium
                LIFE SCIENCES        Bonding                             Conductance and Chemical
                (CHEMISTRY)          s- and p-block Elements             Kinetics
                                     Chemistry of d-block Elements       Organometallics, Bioinorganic
                                                                         Chemistry



                LIFE SCIENCES        Animal           Reproductive       Immunology
                (ZOOLOGY)            Biotechnology  Biology



                                                                         States of Matter and Chemical
                                     Atomic Structure and Chemical       Equilibrium
                PHYSICAL             Bonding                             Conductance and Chemical
                SCIENCES             s- and p-block Elements             Kinetics
                (CHEMISTRY)
                                     Chemistry of d-block Elements       Organometallics, Bioinorganic
                                                                         Chemistry

                PHYSICAL
                SCIENCES             Data Structures                     Computer Networks
                (COMPUTER
                SCIENCE)
                PHYSICAL                                                 II-A Numerical Methods
                SCIENCES             Differential Equations              II-B Probability and Statistics
                (MATHEMATICS)
                PHYSICAL
                SCIENCES             Elements of Modern Physics          Solid State Physics
                (PHYSICS)










                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 42]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[MAITREYI COLLEGE





                DISCIPLINE SPECIFIC ELECTIVE SUBJECTS FOR B.Sc. (HONOURS)
                                  V Semester                            VI Semester
                SUBJECT
                                  DSE I               DSE II            DSE I               DSE II
                                  Analytical                            Industrial    and
                BOTANY            Techniques      in  Biostatistics     Environmental       Bioinformatics
                                  Plant Sciences                        Microbiology
                                  Basic Applications of Computers in
                                  Chemistry                             Molecular           Organometallic
                CHEMISTRY
                                  Green Chemistry                       Modeling            Chemistry
                                  Novel Inorganic Solids
                                                                        I-A Mathematical  II-A Number
                                  I-A Numerical       II-A Probability   Finance            Theory
                                  Analysis            Theory and
                MATHEMATICS  I-B Mathematical  Statistics               I-B Introduction    II-B Linear
                                                                        to Information
                                                                                            Programming
                                  Modeling and        II-B Discrete     Theory and          and
                                  Graph Theory        Mathematics
                                                                        Coding              Applications
                                  Advanced Mathematical Physics         Communication System
                                  Nuclear and Particle Physics
                PHYSICS                                                 Classical Dynamics
                                  Physics of Devices and                Nanomaterials and Applications
                                  Communication
                                                                                            II-A
                                                      II-A                                  Reproductive
                                                      Computational
                                                      Biology           Animal              Biology
                ZOOLOGY           Immunology                                                II-B Wildlife
                                                      II-B Animal       Biotechnology       Conservation
                                                      Behaviour and                         and
                                                      Chronobiology
                                                                                            Management

               IMPORTANT INSTRUCTIONS
                 Every student has to choose interdisciplinary subject as Generic Elective and subject-specific
                  as Discipline Specific Elective papers. The College reserves the right not to offer a particular
                  GE subject/ DSE paper, if the class strength is lower than the stipulated strength. Option for
                  availability of any of the paper may be at the discretion of the respective department.
                 Students  seeking  admission  are  advised  to  read  the  prospectus  and  select  the  subject
                  combination very carefully as change of subject may not be permitted at a later stage.
                 In addition to the regular course of studies, every student is required compulsorily to enroll
                  herself as a cadet for the National Cadet Corps (Women's Wing)/ undergo physical training
                  (Sports)/ join as a volunteer for the National Service Scheme. The options given for this should
                  also be considered carefully while filling up the appropriate column in the admission form.
                 All students are required to join an academic society in any one of the subjects chosen by them.
                 Students staying in the PG or Private hostels are required to submit their present address and
                  phone numbers and intimate the changes, if any.





                                                                 PROSPECTUS 2021-2022               Page 43]]></page></pages></Search>